<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at Mont-St.-Andre-Camp, June 29, 1694 by James Smalwood ...</title>
            <author>Smalwood, James, d. 1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10098</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13776272</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13776272</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60386)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 850:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at Mont-St.-Andre-Camp, June 29, 1694 by James Smalwood ...</title>
                  <author>Smalwood, James, d. 1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jacob Tonson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published now by the King's command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XXII, 36 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101756:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101756:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preached before the KING AT <hi>MONT-St.-ANDRE-Camp, J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NE</hi> 29. 1694.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JAMES SMALWOOD,</hi> Chaplain to the Earl of <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MNEY,</hi> and <hi>HIS MAJESTY's</hi> Firſt Regiment of Foot-Guards. Fellow of <hi>TRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NITY-COLLEGE</hi> in <hi>CAMBRIDGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed now by the King's Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Jacob Tonſon,</hi> at the <hi>Judge</hi>'s <hi>Head,</hi> near the <hi>Inner-Temple-Gate</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:101756:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Mr. <hi>Smalwood</hi>'s SERMON Preached before the KING, AT <hi>MONT-St.-ANDRE-Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101756:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101756:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:101756:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101756:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO His GRACE THE DUKE OF ORMOND,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was Your GRACE's Goodneſs that firſt recommended me to Preach this Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, and therefore I preſume, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Protection, to recommend it to the World: It is, I confeſs, a Hardſhip Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in this Caſe lies under, that Your well-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and good Intention muſt be thus requited, and
<pb facs="tcp:101756:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> that it was not enough that Your Grace did me the Honour that I ſhould appear before ſo Great a Prince; but that I muſt likewiſe lay my Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Imperfections at Your Door now in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: It is indeed an Inconvenience that Great and Good Men ſometimes bring upon themſelves, even by the exerciſe of their Vertues; when they cannot ſhew a Favour, or do an Act of Generoſity, but oftentimes it is returned with troubleſome and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Acknowledgments; or elſe <hi>Their</hi> Patronage muſt be made uſe of to ſcreen the Weakneſſes and Defects of their Clients. However, my Lord, tho the Workmanſhip of this Diſcourſe may be but ſlight and ordinary; yet the Foundation and Ground of it, is firm and ſtrong; and this Advantage my Pen has, that it is engaged in the ſame Cauſe with Your Grace's Sword.</p>
            <p>My Lord, It has been my Good Fortune from Your very Childhood, to have had Opportunities of obſerving all the Steps and Progreſſes of Your Greatneſs; The very Dawnings of Vertue and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage were diſcernable in Your Grace's tender Years, which now ſhine forth Bright, and caſt a Luſtre over the World; even then thoſe ſeeds of Valour and Magnanimity were eaſily to be ſeen which are
<pb facs="tcp:101756:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> now grown up to full Maturity and Perfection; and Your whole Life, my Lord, has roſe by ſuch regular Increaſes and Aſcents, that it appears now like a compleat Piece of Building, the Baſts Strong, the Superſtructure Beautiful and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, the whole Fabrick Perfect, and without a Flaw.</p>
            <p>But, my Lord, within the narrow limits of a Dedication I muſt not think of comprehending Your Grace's Life; only one peculiar Vertue, I, in common with the reſt of Mankind that ever knew You, cannot but mention, and that is, Your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant readineſs of doing Good.</p>
            <p>That extraordinary Quality, that ſingular Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Your own, was, my Lord, the Occaſion of this Diſcourſe; and the Reaſon why it has not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd all this while in Print, when it was His Majeſty's Pleaſure, and the favourable Requeſt of that Honourable Auditory that heard it, that it ſhould; was, becauſe we continued a long time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Camp, and ſince then, I, attending my Duty abroad till now, had not Opportunity of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedient to their Wills; being re-minded by ſome Friends now at home, under the ſafe-Guard
<pb facs="tcp:101756:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> of <hi>Your</hi> great Name, my Lord, I venture it out in Publick, nor do I fear any Cenſures under the Umbrage of ſo great a Patron as Your Grace condeſcends to be to,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your GRACE's Moſt Obedient and Moſt Devoted Servant, <hi>JAMES SMALWOOD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101756:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the KING In the CAMP.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>St. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. part of the 36. <hi>v.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>He that hath no Sword, let him ſell his garment and buy one.</q>
               <q>The Context runs thus, <hi>And he ſaid unto them, when I ſent you without Purſe, or Scrip, or Shooes, lacked ye any thing? And they ſaid, nothing.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Then ſaid he unto them; but now he that hath a Purſe let him take</hi> it, <hi>and likewiſe</hi> his <hi>Scrip, and he that hath no Sword, let him ſell his garment and buy one.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Warlike Aſſembly, I ſhall not take upon me to Read a Lecture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Military Art, or to ſay any thing of the Diſcipline of War, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101756:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> thoſe that underſtand it far better, than either opportunity has given me leave, or my Profeſſion requires: This abſurdity, an Antient <hi>Graecian</hi> Orator was once guilty of before a great General, which was cenſured by a very Judicious Author, as an improper and an aſſuming Action. I ſhall content my ſelf therefore to act within my own Sphere, and accordingly will endeavour, from the Holy Scriptures in general, but more particularly from theſe words of our Bleſſed Saviour, to prove the lawfulneſs of the taking up of Arms by <hi>Chriſtian Men,</hi> at ſome times, and upon ſome occaſions.</p>
            <p>This is the main ſcope and drift of my preſent undertaking; To ſhew, From Chriſt's Command to his Diſciples here in the Text, of ſelling their Cloaths to purchaſe Swords; That the Accoutrements of War are, in ſome caſes, to be provided before bodily Raiment; that Arms may not alwaies yield to the peaceful Gown; but that at ſome ſeaſons of imminent danger, of home-bred Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or a proſpect of Invaſion, or Enmity openly declared; that then War and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of it are to be ſought; then the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101756:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> Bow and the Quiver is to be made ready; then we muſt go, tho' like ſome of the Ancient <hi>Spartans,</hi> half-naked into Battel.</p>
            <p>But before I enter upon the Proof of this, I will clear one Objection, which may with ſome colour be laid before me at the very threſhold, from the Opinion of ſome very Learned and Able Expoſitors.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Hammond, Grotius,</hi> and ſome others, ſay, that theſe Words of our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our are not to be taken Literally, but Figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Lord and Maſter, was now near the time of his departure out of the World; The Captain of our Salvation, was now about laying down the great Commiſſion he had received from his Father; and now when he was taking leave of his Diſciples, thoſe Fellow-Souldiers of his, thoſe who had hitherto fought the ſame good fight with himſelf, againſt all the Powers of the World, or the Devil, thoſe who under his care and conduct had ſerved ſecurely, and were protected ſafely, to whom he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly upon their ſeveral great and hazardous
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101756:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> Expeditions, given Orders, to <hi>Provide neither</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 9.</note> 
               <hi>gold, nor ſilver, nor braſs in their purſes, nor ſcrip for their journey, neither two coats, neither ſhooes, nor yet ſtaves;</hi> yet to them now he ſpeaks otherwiſe, he foreſees, that now ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly far more calamitous and perillous times would come, the conflicts they were to meet with both Corporal and Spiritual would be great, the dangers they were to encounter inevitable; he therefore Arms them now with an extraordinary Courage, and adviſes them to lay in good Proviſions: The <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom</hi> himſelf would be abſent, and they muſt not expect any Perſonal Aſſiſtance or Subſiſtence from him; ſo that it would not now be ſufficient to <hi>ſhake off the duſt of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 14.</note> 
               <hi>their feet againſt a Houſe or a City, that would not receive</hi> and entertain them kindly, but they muſt ſupply themſelves with all Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries requiſite, both for the Maintenance and Defence of their Perſons; they muſt not only fill their Purſes and their Scrips<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but they muſt provide themſelves too of Weapons, nay, they who had no Swords, were obliged to ſell even their very Garments and buy them.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101756:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> By all this, ſay theſe Learned Perſons, is nothing more meant by our Saviour, than that his Diſciples ſhould Arm their <hi>Minds,</hi> againſt all the Spiritual Oppoſitions, and againſt all the Temporal Hardſhips they might meet with in the World.</p>
            <p>This perhaps might have been the Figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative meaning of our Saviour, That now he was going from the Head of his Diſciples, They ſhould put on a greater firmneſs and reſolution of <hi>Mind,</hi> Arm their <hi>Spirits</hi> with an undaunted Courage and readineſs to grapple with the ſevereſt Trials, and to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount all difficulties; and the <hi>Sword</hi> here in my Text, might poſſibly be uſed in the ſame Senſe by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> that St. <hi>Paul</hi> uſes the <hi>Sword</hi> of the Spirit, the <hi>Shield</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.</note> of Faith, the <hi>Helmet</hi> of Salvation, or any of the other parts of Armory, he there furniſhes out his Chriſtian Warrior with. However, admitting this Metaphorical acceptation of the Words, I ſee no abſurdity or falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, in taking the Text in the more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious and literal ſignification: St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> I am ſure, a Father of no mean Authority, takes this very Text of Scripture, in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101756:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> plain and verbal importance, and makes uſe of it for an Argument againſt the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichees,</hi> a whimſical Sect of People, who decried all manner of uſe of Secular Arms, as unjuſtifiable amongſt Chriſtian Men. And it may be preſumed, St. <hi>Peter</hi> that great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, underſtood our Saviour according to the Letter too; for preſently after the words were ſpoke, when he ſaw his Maſter fall into the violent hands of the High-Prieſt's Servants, he drew his Sword, and with it, gave a plain demonſtration in what Senſe he took the words. Nay, this was not only St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s apprehenſion of theſe Words, but 'tis to be ſuppoſed, of all the Apoſtles likewiſe, for we find in the following Verſe their joint Anſwer: <hi>He that has no Sword, let him ſell his Garment and buy one,</hi> ſays our Saviour, <hi>And they ſaid, Lord, behold here are two Swords, And he ſaid unto them it is enough.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, thus much certainly may very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and very agreeably too to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, be inferr'd from this Text, That tho' Spiritual Arms are the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans commendable Weapons, in the Times of Perſecutions and Oppreſſions; and a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101756:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Mind is then always required; yet even the outward Corporal Means of juſt Defence or Offence, are allowed Chriſtians as well as other Men.</p>
            <p>This is a Poſition, that the ſtricteſt of our Saviour Chriſt's Precepts, does not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict or diſprove, for altho Patience in Perſecutions, long-ſuffering of Injuries, love of very Enemies, are recommended to us as the moſt ſublime Chriſtian Vertues; altho by ſuch Commands as this, <hi>Unto him that ſmiteth thee on the one Cheek, turn the other;</hi> we are admoniſh'd to paſs by all trivial and accidental Injuries in common Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; altho the firſt Methods of the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel, were gentle and peaceable, and the ſame Methods ought ſtill to be practis'd in the Conſervation of it: Yet did I never meet with any ſo very Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualized a Caſuiſt, that carried on the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſelf-reſignation ſo high, but that it was always allowed, That when private Mens Lives are in danger; and much more, when the Publick Life of the State is in jeopardy; and moſt of all, when Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf is in hazard of being ſubverted or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101756:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> corrupted, that then the free uſe of all Means of both Perſonal and Publick Security, were never Prohibited by our Saviour.</p>
            <p>This ſlender Objection being thus removed, I ſhall not ſcruple to take the Text in a Grammatical and Literal Senſe, and from it ſo conſidered,</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall lay down this for a Poſitive and Unconteſtable Aſſertion; That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Doctrines of Humility, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Submiſſion, Forgiving of Injuries, Forbearance of Revenge, which the Goſpel of Chriſt, and the Writings of the Apoſtles ſo much preſs upon us, and which are the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Weapons of our Warfare here in this World; yet ſtill the Armour of the Body, and the juſt uſe of material Weapons, is, and in all Ages of the World before and ſince Chriſtianity, was Lawful; nay, at ſome times, and in ſome conditions of Affairs, War is neceſſary, and more the Duty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian People, than a ſlothful Peace.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I will enquire at what Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and Seaſons Arms may be taken up.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101756:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> III. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I will make it appear, that our preſent War is to be juſtified by all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Arguments that can be required for the carrying on of any.</p>
            <p>I. <hi>Firſt,</hi> I am to prove the warrantableneſs of War amongſt Chriſtian People; and one would think, I needed not to ſpend much time in making good that univerſal and avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Opinion; That all defenſive and offenſive Means of Safety, which amongſt all Men are allowable, are equally ſo to Chriſtians, as to any other part of Mankind.</p>
            <p>That War was both practiſed in the moſt ancient Seaſons of the World, and not only countenanced, but directed and in a manner proclaimed too by God himſelf, is a thing plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſeen in many Places of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; <hi>Moſes</hi> was commanded to raiſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and to form an Army by God's own ſpecial Order; <hi>Abraham</hi> commenced a War for the reſcue of his Brother <hi>Lot;</hi> and many other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances might be produc'd out of the Old Teſtament; but let us look into the New, the Precepts of which are far more obligatory
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101756:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> to us Chriſtians, and there we ſhall find the Equity of Arms as much eſtabliſh'd amongſt the Chriſtians, as they were made uſe of amongſt the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> For what did our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour intend by theſe Words, <hi>If my Kingdom were of this World, then would my Servants fight, that I ſhould not be delivered to the</hi> Jews; what, I ſay, could our Saviour here mean, but that the taking up of Arms, at ſome Exigences of time, was a thing not only practicable, but warrantable? <hi>If my Kingdom were of this World,</hi> that is, if I did really pretend to erect any temporal and material Kingdom in this World, any more than a ſpiritual Soveraignty over Souls; then, as it is Cuſtomary with all earthly Princes in ſuch Caſes, rather than be thus uſed by theſe <hi>Jews,</hi> would I raiſe an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to defend my Perſon, and to revenge the Injuries I have unjuſtly received at their Hands; then would I and my Army fight, as it is the manner of all worldly Princes to do, whenever their Dominions and Prerogatives are wrongfully invaded, or their Perſons ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominiouſly treated. This ſeems to me to be the Meaning and Purport of that Text.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101756:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> But may not this Countenancing of War ſeem a moſt prepoſterous and ſurprizing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for the Prince of Peace to deliver? How is this conſiſtent with his own Life and Converſation, which was nothing elſe but one continued Act of Suffering? How comes He that endured all the Barbarous Uſage, Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetings, Spittings upon, Scourgings, that was led like a Sheep to the Slaughter, and like a Lamb that is Dummb? How comes He now to open his Mouth ſo angrily, and to breath forth nothing but War and Battel? How is it, that He, who at another time ſends out his Apoſtles without any Equipage or the leaſt Furniture, only with this poor Commiſſion, <hi>Go and teach all Nations, and lo I am with you,</hi> how is it that now he recommends to them the Inſtruments of War, and makes Swords ſuch uſeful, ſuch indiſpenſible Companions of their Travels, that, rather than want them, he bids them Pawn and ſell their very Cloaths to buy them? Nay, how comes our Saviour, here in my Text, to prefer Swords before Garments, which was juſt before he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd into the Hands of his Enemies, and looked as if he intended ſome Oppoſition
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101756:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> againſt them, yet preſently after, when he was ſiez'd by the High Prieſt's Officers, and <hi>Peter</hi> endeavoured to reſcue him, by wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of them, He there alters his Mind quite, and rebukes <hi>Peter</hi> for drawing his Sword with this ſevere Reprimand, <hi>Put up thy Sword into its Place, he that taketh the Sword ſhall periſh by the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two remarkable Sentences of our Saviour, that in my Text, and this to St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> may at firſt hearing appear liable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Interpretations; But if we rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, we ſhall find they do not only not thwart or invalidate one the other, but agree very well, and taking them both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we may learn from them the whole Chriſtian Doctrine of War, and what uſe of ſecular Arms the Goſpel permits, and what it condemns.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt</hi> then, St. <hi>Peter</hi> out of an over-ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Paſſion, and an unſeaſonable Zeal, when his Maſter was apprehended by the Miniſters of the Chief Prieſts and Elders <hi>drew his Sword and ſtruck a Servant of the High Prieſt, and ſmote of his Ear.</hi> This was done 'tis true, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Chriſt himſelf, of the moſt Perfect
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101756:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Innocence that ever appeared in the World, it was too upon a Man that was performing a moſt unjuſt Act of Violence in it ſelf, but what he was Commiſſioned to do by Publick Authority; our Saviour therefore reproves St. <hi>Peter</hi> for ſtriking with the Sword without a ſufficient Warrant, and blames the Fact, as an illegal Attempt of a Private Man againſt a Publick Officer ſet on work by a lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate: But we are not to conclude that our Bleſſed Saviour, by this Check given to St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> did abſolutely prohibit all manner of uſing the Sword amongſt Chriſtians; if ſo, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate himſelf is prohibited the uſe of it, who we are told by the Apoſtle, <hi>beareth not the Sword in vain,</hi> but indeed he cannot be ſaid to bear it otherwiſe than in vain, if he may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have the liberty to draw it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, We muſt conſider when our Saviour gave this charge to his Diſciples, they were then launching out into the wide World, where they muſt expect to meet with many Rubbs, and Dangers, therefore he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes them to ſtand upon their own Legs, and be continually upon their Guard, that they ſhould be Watchful and Cautious, able
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101756:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> to repel any Injury or Violence offered to them, with Courage, and that therefore they ſhould provide themſelves of means neceſſary and requiſite thereunto; In the foregoing Verſe he appeals to them, and asks them, if they had any Complaints to make to him of his neglect of them, or whether they had wanted any thing in his Service, which they freely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged they had not: He proceeds now he is leaving them, to bid them take all Care Men can of themſelves, to be ſure always to have their <hi>Purſes</hi> and their <hi>Scrips</hi> in good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and above all, to be well furniſh'd with good Arms, not to act the leaſt Private Injury, but to defend themſelves as much as may be againſt all.</p>
            <p>So that our Saviour by the Check he uſed to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> does no more than admoniſh all Private Chriſtians to abſtain from paſſionate, giddy, and unwarrantable Quarrels, and not to confront Publick Authority, leaving it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs lawful for ſuperiour Magiſtrates to unſheath their Swords in Defence of General Rights.</p>
            <p>And by the Words of my Text he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, that all Chriſtians may juſtly make
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101756:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> Proviſion againſt all Difficulties and Dangers that may happen to be encountred with in this World, and conſequently againſt all wrongful Inſults, Incroachments, or Invaſions, upon either their Perſons or their Properties; ſo that theſe two Texts are ſo far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting one the other, that both joyn'd and conſidered together, make up an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Rule for the uſe of the Sword.</p>
            <p>The concluſion from both may be this; That although it is not lawful for every Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Man to revenge Perſonal Injuries, or to make his own Sword the Judge of Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which belong properly to the deciſion of the Magiſtrate, much leſs to reſiſt Publick Juſtice, whether in a wrong or a right Cauſe; yet a Man's Bodily Preſervation and Defence from ſuddain Attacks, God has in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure committed to himſelf and his own Sword; And it is lawful, tho' not to offer Injuries, yet to reſiſt forcible Ones with Force; but chiefly it is lawful for Men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to draw the Sword againſt Publick Injuries, in aſſiſting the Civil State of which they are Members, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it calls for their Aid, being either openly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101756:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> threatned from Abroad, or ſecretly undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at home.</p>
            <p>It was therefore a wrong determination of one of the Ancient Fathers, to infer from our Saviour's Command to St. <hi>Peter</hi> to put up his Sword, that it is unlawful for Chriſtians at any time to draw theirs, and that all Military Employments are conſequently criminal. This is an Opinion not only not to be maintain'd by any Evangelical Writing, but it is really abſurd in it ſelf; for what would that be but to make Criſtianity a Prey to its inſatiable, and a Laughing-Stock to its inſolent Enemies? This were to proſtitute the Lives and Fortunes of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to the outragious Wills of their profeſs'd Enemies, <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans;</hi> This were the readieſt means for Kings and Princes to become uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Creatures; This were to deprive good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Opportunities of exerting their Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and of rewards juſtly due to <hi>Them,</hi> who venture their lives for their Church and Country when under any Oppreſſion; Nay, this were to blacken the Honour of all thoſe ancient Warriours, who fought ſo valiantly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101756:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> for the ſake of Religion againſt <hi>Infidels</hi> and <hi>Barbarians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any Man ſhall object, that ſome of the Primitive Chriſtians were of Opinion that the uſe of the Sword was unlawful, and that therefore it is ſtill ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It may be anſwered, that it was not the general and eſtabliſh'd Opinion of the Primitive Church, but of ſome particular Men, that affected an harmleſs kind of Life, and were fond of being reputed the Fathers of ſome extraordinary and more than Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Opinions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some of the Primitive Chiſtians were ſo nicely Conſciencious, that they would not liſt themſelves Souldiers, nor take up Arms, becauſe ſome of their Emperours, tho lawful, were Heathens, and their Conſciences were ſo ſcrupulous, that that they could not ſerve them, whilſt others, and with as good a Conſcience, took the Military Oath, and did ſerve; with as good a Conſcience, I ſay; for the Military Oath at that time, tendered to thoſe that were willing to go into the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, interfered not the leaſt with any Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Religion, it forced no Man to worſhip their falſe Gods, it was no Teſt of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101756:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> Conſcience, any farther than an Obligation to obſerve the Articles of War, to obey ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Officers, to ſubmit to Words of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and whatever outward Services Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Laws require.</p>
            <p>We read, that ſome of the <hi>Jews</hi> deſir'd ſometimes an exemption from Military Employments, leſt their frequent being upon Duty might prevent their exact Obſervance of all the Niceties of the Law; and they might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled ſometimes to bear Arms upon the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or in their Marches to exceed a <hi>Sabbath-Day's-Journey.</hi> So amongſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> there were ſome perhaps, at the beginning of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, ſo very refined, that might upon a ſcruple of Conſcience, decline taking up of Arms: The Primitive Chriſtians were enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with a mighty Zeal to all Holy and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blime Performances; the very <hi>Counſels</hi> of the Goſpel had with them the force of <hi>Poſitive Commands,</hi> and a great many of them, out of a Pious Weakneſs, rather than Sound Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, like ſome of our modern Sectaries, would do things that were never directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Scriptures; thus ſome of them thought it a Sin to Marry, becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> prefers a Single Life; ſome again, becauſe our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101756:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> Saviour ſays, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> choſe rather to looſe their Dues, than they would take an Oath in a Court of Juſtice to maintain them. But this is no Argument againſt the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſtians; what a few out of their exalted, or perhaps diſtempered Judgments ſhall do, can never oblige all Mankind to the ſame Practice, without a poſitive Precept for the ſame; if a Sick-Brained Man ſhall, becauſe our ſaviour checked St. <hi>Peter</hi> for draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Sword, or becauſe it is written, <hi>unto him that ſmiteth thee on the one Cheek turn the other.</hi> If, I ſay, any wilful Perſon, ſhall, out of his own miſ-underſtanding of theſe Paſſages, reſolve to bear all Injuries and Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that can be offered him, this can be no Rule to Mankind, we are prompted other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the Law of Nature, and the Law of Chriſt did never aboliſh that.</p>
            <p>I would not be miſtaken; the Law of Chriſt I aſſert, did never utterly diſannul and abrogate the Law of Nature; but this it does, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains and corrects the Viſciouſneſs of it: The Law of Nature, and the Dictates of Reaſon were Imprinted on the Hearts of Men by the Finger of God, and the Rules and Precepts of the Goſpel were drawn up by the ſame
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101756:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Hand, ſo that ſince the ſame God was the Author of both, they cannot contradict each other, tho the latter does govern and curb the Exorbitances of the former; every thing that Nature prompts or provokes us to, is not to be done; becauſe we have ſeveral Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Precepts againſt the corrupt Inclinations of it; But whatever Nature directs, and the ſame is not only permitted, but to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained alſo, and juſtified by the Laws of Chriſt, that certainly is Lawful and practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by Chriſtian Men.</p>
            <p>The Reſult and Inference from hence is this, That the taking up Arms upon a juſt Account, and allowable Conditions, is Lawful, as a thing as well permitted by the Law of Chriſt, as we are inclin'd and directed to it by the Law of Nature.</p>
            <p>And that Nature does direct Mankind to a Defence againſt all outward Annoyances, and an Offence of thoſe that manifeſtly declare themſelves Enemies to it, not only every Man's own Breaſt, but every Author in all Ages informs us. This is a Law, ſays <hi>Tully, Non Scripta, ſed Nata, &amp;c.</hi> Not <note place="margin">Orat. pro Tit. An. Mil.</note> drawn up in Writing for us, but Born with us, which we have not learned or acquired by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101756:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Reading, but it was inſtilled into our very Beings, That, whenever our Lives are in any Perils, either from treacherous Thieves and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſines, or from open Enemies, then all means of freeing our ſelves and obtaining Safety, are Juſt and Honourable; This Principle was looked upon by the <hi>Romans</hi> ſo very Juſt and Reaſonable, that they transfer'd it into their Twelve Tables, and made it Authentick by Law.</p>
            <p>I would not be miſ-apprehended; While I juſtifie the War, and taking up of Arms by the Law of Nature, I would not be underſtood to countenance all Acts of Violence, or Rapine, or Blood-ſhedding, or that it were Naturally Lawful for the Stronger Part of Mankind, to prey upon, or devour the Weaker; For this, tho Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> has been pleas'd ſo to ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize it, is not any part of the Law of Nature, Humane Nature rightly diſpoſed and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved, is not of that fierce and brutal Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>Do as you would be done by; Give every Man his Due,</hi> and ſuch like, are Laws of Nature; all which, tend to the Welfare and Quiet of Mankind: Humane Nature is Gentle, and Tractable, and Courteous, and is ſo far a-kin even to Chriſtian Charity it ſelf, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101756:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> it can <hi>ſuffer long;</hi> nor will it be <hi>eaſily provoked;</hi> But when the Man is juſtly provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and the furious Enemy breaks in violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon him, then it is, that Nature reaches out the Sword to him, and Chriſtianity for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids him not the uſe of it.</p>
            <p>Thus far my Firſt Propoſition ſtands good, and thus far the taking up of Arms is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I will now enquire at what Seaſons and Conjunctures of Time, Arms may be moſt juſtly, and with trueſt Praiſe employed; and that</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In reſpect of Private Perſons.</item>
               <item>2. In reſpect of Publick States and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of Private Perſons; A Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Man may unqueſtionably draw his Sword when aſſaulted and put in danger of his Life; Murder or the taking away a Man's Life upon deliberation and with a premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Malice, is both a very heinous Sin, and very prejudicial to the Government; and therefore it falls under the cognizance of the common Law; but if I am ſet upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awars, and brought to the unavoidable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101756:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> of either being killed my ſelf, or by killing my Adverſary to ſave my ſelf, here not only Nature and common Reaſon advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes me to ſecure my Perſon, but the Law too acquits me of the Fact. In this caſe, ſays the <hi>Heathen Orator,</hi> the Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nives and is ſilent, nor does it expect <note place="margin">Silent Leges inter Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, nec ſe Expectari ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, quum ei, qui expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctare velit, ante injuſta Poena luenda ſit quam ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta repetenda. Pro Tit. An. Mil.</note> to be refer'd to, when a Man, tho he is willing perhaps the Law ſhould be his Judge, may wrongfully ſuffer, before he can legally right himſelf. Whenever therefore any ſingle Man is ſo ſtreightned that his Sword muſt remove his Adverſary, before he can be ſure of himſelf, there the taking away of the Aggreſſor's Life, is as Commendable and Juſt as it is Natural. This is a Truth, ſays the ſame Author, that Men of Learning are convinced of by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Uncivilized and Barbarous People are taught by the Power of Reaſon, all Nations Practice by Cuſtom, and even Brute and Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational Creatures are guided to by Nature.</p>
            <p>But for Revenge of Injuries received, it is not Lawful for a Private Man to have recourſe to his own Sword; that is a Privelege not to be uſurp'd by every Single Perſon: It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing elſe but a perfect Invaſion upon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101756:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> Publick Athority, and an open treſpaſs upon Juſtice; That too common Cuſtom amongſt us of Mens doing themſelves Right, as it is falſly Phraſed, by Private Duels. It is not only a Violation, but a rude Contempt of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to which they belong, that Private Men ſhould take the Sword of Juſtice into their own Hands, and take upon themſelves to redreſs thoſe Grievances which they have recieved, the doing of which, is the ſole Buſineſs, as well as the undoubted Prerogative of the Magiſtrate; and then that Military Men ſhould upon every imaginary Pique, or trifling Affront, every Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Honour hazard their Lives one among another, which might more Honourably be ventured in the Service of God and their King, that brave and gallant Men ſhould thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably fall, is not only a great pity, but a great Damage and Diſ-ſervice too to the Cauſe they are publickly engaged for; <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> tells us of Two of his Officers that had a Quarrel, and that their way of ending the Diſpute, was not in a ſingle Duel behind a Hedge, but by challenging and defying one another in an open Engagement with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, who ſhould approve himſelf then the braver Man; This was Heroically performed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101756:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> and like true <hi>Romans:</hi> For they who were the moſt Victorious Nation of the Ancient World, never practiſed this miſtaken way of Honour, called Duelling: Nay, that very Nation of the modern World, that principally intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced it, has now quite forgot it. The <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> methinks ſhould not eſteem that a part of Bravery, which the Old <hi>Romans,</hi> whoſe greatneſs of Mind they do in other things come up to, never thought ſo: But let us learn from our very Enemies, for Vertues are to be appoved of even in them, as we follow them in other Faſhions, ſo to imitate them in this; but if that Conſideration will not take place with us, let us leave of this Vitious Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome in very deſpight of them, that <hi>They</hi> may not by this have any Advantage over us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As by Private Men for ſafety, tho not for revenge, the Sword may be juſtly drawn, ſo much more by all in a Publick Cauſe, and then not only for Safety, but for Revenge. The repaying of Vengeance is a Privelege God claims to himſelf, and to none in this World but to the Magiſtrate of Juſtice has God committed that Power: The right of Puniſhment is Originally inveſted in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, tho he is pleaſed to commit the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101756:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> of it to the Hand and Management of Man: And as the Sheriff does inflict the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment on a Malefactor, in the Name, and on the Behalf of the King, ſo does the King himſelf derive his Power and Right of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting Wickedneſs, and Exerciſing the Sword, from God: This is a Truth, that not only holds good in formal Proceſſes of Law againſt Murderers, Thieves, or any other Diſturbers of the Civil Peace and Societies of Men; but alſo in national Grievances and Oppreſſions: Whenever any People or Government is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther invaded or threatened; when national In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries are apparently deſigned or actually of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, when Ruine and Deſolation, like the Father of them, go about ſeeking whom they may devour, and nothing can ſatisfie them till they are glutted with the Poſſeſſions of their Neighbours round about them; in a Word, when the boundleſs Ambition of any one Potentate ſhall thirſt after nothing leſs than an Univerſal Dominion, then certainly to put a Hook into the Noſe of this rowling <hi>Leviathan,</hi> then to levy a War, and to endeavour to put a ſtop to this ſwelling Torrent, then to draw the Sword and to oppoſe this impetuous Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruy, is not only Lawful, but Neceſſary.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101756:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> And certainly if there ever was any Cauſe, any time ſince Chriſtianity was firſt heard of, to which either Reaſon has more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily perſuaded, or Religion recommended, The uſe of the Sword, and the due Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for uſing it, This of ours is the Cauſe, this the Time, which brings me to my Third and laſt thing I propoſed to ſhew, which was,</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that the War we are at preſent engaged in, has all the Arguments to juſtifie it, that can be required for the carrying on of any.</p>
            <p>Some of the Doctors of the Schools tell us, there are Four Conditions requiſite to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie a War;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Cauſe muſt be juſt,</item>
               <item>2. The Authority muſt be lawful,</item>
               <item>3. The Manner of it muſt be fair,</item>
               <item>4. The End propos'd muſt be for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good.</item>
            </list>
            <p>It would be too tedious to enlarge upon upon every Condition ſeperately. The War now undertaken, and hitherto (bleſſed be God) ſucceſsfully carryed on by the Confederate Chriſtian Princes, was concerted and raiſed certainly upon the juſteſt Cauſe whatever, which was the vindication of both Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101756:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Temporal Rights: The Authority is unqueſtionable, which is founded on the Unanimous Conſent of ſo many Princes and Potentates, who are God's Delegates here upon Earth: The Manner is fair, which is Defenſive againſt the unjuſt Incurſions of one great Diſturber of the Chriſtian World: And the End propoſed is for the Publick Good, which, 'tis to be hoped, may be an honourable and an advantageous Peace.</p>
            <p>This is the Nature of our Preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy; the Grounds and Occaſion of it may be maintained by all the Laws of God and Man; the Methods it is ſupported by and nouriſhed are honeſt and equitable; and the Ends we aim at are every way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Holy Religion of Chriſt, which preſcribes Peace and Quiet, Charity to Neighbours, and Good Will to all Men.</p>
            <p>This indeed is the beſt, and the only true Cauſe, for which all good Subjects are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Conſcience to fight, The Cauſe of God and their Country; the Goodneſs of which appears from the ſeveral Intereſts uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in it: For in this, not only the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Nations to which we belong our ſelves, not only the Security of our own
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101756:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> Perſons is involved, but the Inheritances and Poſſeſſions, the Honour and Intereſt of moſt of the Chriſtians of <hi>Europe</hi> are inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt and woven: And that ſo mighty a Deſign ſhould all this while be ſo ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully carried on, that ſo many different Parties and States ſhould joyn, and as firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly combine as the Heart of one Man, This is a wonderful thing, and muſt needs point out the Almighty Contriver of it; <hi>This is the Lord's doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes: This is the Lord mighty in Battle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Succeſs of King <hi>Cyrus</hi> when he went againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> is very memorable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable: We meet with ſeveral Inſtances of an Almighty and Over-ruling Power throughout that whole Expedition: For what was it elſe, but the Hand of God, who governs and commands the Hearts of Men, that brought in ſo many Confederate Forces to his Aſſiſtance, ſome of which were not only Allies, but even Subjects to the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> without whoſe concurring help the whole Enterpriſe had miſcarried? That great Victory is not to be imputed to the ſole Conduct and Management of King <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi> or indeed, to the Strength of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101756:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> but to him, to whom (as the Prophet ſpeaks) <hi>All Nations are as the drop of a Bucket.</hi> He that told <hi>Cyrus, I have girded thee, tho thou haſt not known me.</hi> He it was that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Means and effected the Work; He <hi>ſet up the Standard, and blew the Trumpet, and prepared the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have great Reaſon to acknowledge the ſame Power with us too; <hi>He</hi> it is that goeth forth with our Armies to Battle, and protects us againſt all the cloſe and invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Deſigns of our Enemies; He it is that has influenced the Councils of ſo many diſtinct Governments, to join their Forces againſt one mighty Devourer of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: And who may this potent Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, who may this great Incendiary of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> be? Even he, who nevertheleſs is not aſhamed to bear the Title of the moſt <hi>Chriſtian King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I cannot but reflect upon what Spirit it muſt be that does actuate this migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Man, that no Laws, either Humane or Divine, can faſten any Obligations on him: How many Treaties of Peace has he tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon and broke? What Nation round about him has not He been unfaithful to?
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101756:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> It were ſuperfluous to mention his Attempt upon <hi>Spain</hi> after the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace; <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and <hi>Nimegue,</hi> and his late Violation of the Truce agreed upon by his own Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal for Twenty Years, do all teſtifie againſt him: And above all, his entring into a League Offenſive and Defenſive with the <hi>Turk,</hi> the known and declared Enemy of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> at a time too when that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire was in its Declination, ſhews plainly how much his Ambition overſways his Faith and Honour, and how every way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving he is of the Title of the moſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt this Man, if their Temporal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts were not concerned, the very regard to the Chriſtian Religion would juſtly Arm all the Profeſſors of it. But the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Worldly Peace and Quiet, the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of our proper Poſſeſſions, the free Exerciſe of Trade, the Recovery of what has been forcibly uſurped, the requiring of Satisfaction for the Breach of Truſt and Honour, as well as the Vindication of our moſt Holy Religion; and many other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations do concur to recommend and juſtifie this preſent Cauſe of ours.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101756:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> And This is a Cauſe, for which ſure no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but our own Sins can hinder God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty in his due time more ſignally to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear: This is a Cauſe that I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, and dare almoſt preſage, will, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God's Chaſtiſments ſhall have wrought their intended Effects upon us, prove ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful: To this let every Man ſtretch his Arm; in This let all engage with Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Alacrity; in This great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our Countrymen have already ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured and loſt their Lives; <hi>One</hi> of our moſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>D. of</hi> O.</note> noble Patriots moſt eminently hazarded his: For this it is that our moſt Gracious <hi>KING</hi> does ſo often chooſe to haraſs and expoſe <hi>His Sacred Perſon.</hi> This then, after ſo great an Example, all of us ſhould in our ſeveral Stations manfully maintain and ſtand up for: For this every True Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that has no <hi>Sword,</hi> ſhould, if need ſo require, <hi>ſell his Garment and buy one;</hi> we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch Laws and Liberties to defend, we having ſuch a Church and Faith to contend for, we having ſuch a Faith's-Defender, whom we ought to ſerve with our Purſes, our Scrips, our Swords, our Lives.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
